Guide to the Jonathan Edwards Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Writings of Jonathan Edwards, c. 1720-84; Series I; 10.3; (21 boxes)
  - SERMONS
    - MATT. 13:47-50: "Obs. 4. Wicked men cannot always enjoy their element but must be first or last be forever separated from it" (p. 1), incomplete, 1746 May (Box 6, Folder 478)
    - MATT. 13:47-50: "Obs. 6. This world must come to an end" (p. 1) "Obs. 7. When the full number of the elect shall be gathered in the end of the world will come soon" (p. 17), 1746 Jun (Box 6, Folder 479)
    - MATT. 13:47-50: "Obs. 8. God will hereafter deal with the righteous as men are wont to treat that which they prize as the portion they live upon" (p. 1) "Obs. 9. God will hereafter cast away any unsound professors" (p. 17), 1746 Jun (Box 6, Folder 480)
    - MATT. 13:47-50: "Obs. 10. God makes use of the ministry of angels in affairs relating to the eternal state of mankind" (p. 1), 1746 Jun (Box 6, Folder 481)
    - MATT. 13:47-50: "Obs. 11. Wicked men will hereafter be cast into a furnace of fire", 1746 Jul (Box 6, Folder 482)
    - MATT. 13:47-50: "Obs. 12. In the misery of the damned there will be a mixture of sorrow and rage" (p. 1), 1746 Jul (Box 6, Folder 483)
    - MATT. 13:47-50: "So none ought to come into the Christian church but good men. But because ministers can't know men's hearts every sort will come in, good and bad. As there will be some bad fish in the net, so there will be some bad men in the kingdom of Christ" (p. 2), 1750 Jan
      See: Box 13, folder 1037
    - MATT. 14:12: "When anyone is taken away by death that has been eminent in the work of the gospel ministry, tis suitable that such as are bereaved thereby should go and spread their sorrows before Jesus" (p. 4), 1740, 1741 (Box 6, Folder 484)
    - MATT. 15:26: "There is a great difference between converted and unconverted men" (p. 3) (Box 6, Folder 485)
    - MATT. 16:15: "It concerns all that live under the gospel to be determined in their own minds who that Jesus was about whom there was so much ado among the Jews in the days of Pontius Pilate" (p. 1), 1748/9, 1756 (Box 7, Folder 486)
    - MATT. 16:17: "That there is such a thing as a spiritual and divine light, immediately imparted to the soul by God, of a different nature from any that is obtained by natural means" (p. 4), 1733 Aug (Box 7, Folder 487)
      Published as Divine and Supernatural Light
    - MATT. 16:18: "Prop. 1. Shew how the church of Christ is built upon a rock. II. How that therefore the gates of hell never have and never will prevail against it" (p. 3), 1745/6 Mar 13 (Box 7, Folder 488)
      "Fast occasioned by the rebellion"
    - MATT. 16:21-23: "It was a thing exceeding offensive to Christ to hear said anything against those great sufferings which he came into the world to undergo" (p. 4) (Box 7, Folder 489)
    - MATT. 16:24: "We can't be some of Christ's people unless we deny ourselves and in many things go contrary to our natural inclination" (p. 1), 1752 Jan (Box 7, Folder 490)
    - MATT. 16:26: "That the salvation of the soul is a thing of vastly more worth and importance than the whole world" (p. 3), two sermons
      See: Box 13, folders 1038-1039
    - MATT. 16:26: "1. The whole world is not a sufficient price to receive to make up for the loss of the soul. 2. When once the soul is lost the whole world would not be a sufficient price to give to recover it" (p. 5), 1734 Oct (Box 7, Folder 491)
    - MATT. 17:1-5: "The subject: Christ's transfiguration" (p. 4), 1744, 1753 (Box 7, Folder 492)
    - MATT. 17:5: "I. Christ is the Son of God...Christ is both God and man...So he was the Son of God from all eternity" (p. 1), 1753 May
      See: Box 13, folder 1040
    - MATT. 18:7: "We live in a world that has woe denounced against it. [or:] That God hath denounced woe against this world" (p. 5), 1734 May (Box 7, Folder 493)
    - MATT. 18:8-9: "It may well be enough to make us take heed to ourselves that we in the present state as it were set between heaven and hell", 1737 Apr (Box 7, Folder 494)
    - MATT. 18:20: "I would 1. Shew what it is for persons to come together in Christ's name. 2. In what sense Christ will be in the midst of those that thus come together. & 3. Shew that Christ won't fail them to be in the midst of those that come together in his name though they be very few" (p. 2), [ca. 1740-42] (Box 7, Folder 495)
    - MATT. 21:5: "The external meanness of Christ's appearance in the world is a thing worthy of the highest admiration" (p. 3), n.d.
      See: Box 13, folder 1041
    - MATT. 21:31: "Self-righteousness is one of the greatest banes of the souls of men" (p. 3), 1747/8 Jan (Box 7, Folder 496)
    - MATT. 22:1-14: "Obs. 1. The church of Christ is as it were married to Christ" (p. 1), 1755 Apr
      See: Box 13, folder 1042
    - MATT. 22:14: "There are but few even of those that live under the calls of the gospel that shall be saved," incomplete (Box 7, Folder 497)
    - MATT. 22:37-38: "1. What it is to love God. 2. The reason why we ought to love him. 3. Why [we ought to love him] with all our heart. 4. How this is the greatest of all the commandments" (p. 1), 1753 Apr
      See: Box 13, folder 1043
    - MATT. 22:39: "That we should love all men but tis not meant that we should love all alike. Love some more than others because they deserve more love" (p. 7), 1753 Apr
      See: Box 13, folder 1044
    - MATT. 23:15: "Wicked men are the children of hell" (p. 5), 1738/9 Jan (Box 7, Folder 498)
    - MATT. 23:27: "Wicked men's bodies are as it were the sepulchres of their souls" (p. 3), 1736/7 Mar (Box 7, Folder 499)
    - MATT. 23:33: "Tis in itself most rational to suppose that wicked men should be most extremely and eternally miserable in another world" (p. 5), 1737 Jul (Box 7, Folder 500)
    - MATT. 23:37: "[Christ] is ready to receive sinners and love 'em and shew great mercy to 'em if they will come to him" (p. 1), 1754 Jan
      See: Box 13, folder 1045
    - MATT. 24:12-13: "Tis necessary for those that have religious affections and seem to have a love to Christ, that they should endure to the end in order to their being saved" (p. 1), 1742 Nov (Box 7, Folder 501)
    - MATT. 24:35: "That God never fails of his word" (p. 3), n.d. (Box 7, Folder 502)
    - MATT. 24:43: "Many wicked men, if they knew how near death was, would not do as they do" (p. 1), n.d. (Box 7, Folder 503)
    - MATT. 25:1: "The church is espoused to the Lord Jesus Christ" (p. 3), 1737 Nov (Box 7, Folder 504)
      Introductory sermon to series on the parable of the ten virgins
    - MATT. 25:1-12: "I. The visible church of Christ is made up of true and false Christians. II. Thes two sorts of Christians do in many things agree, and yet in many other things greatly differ", 1737 Dec (Box 7, Folder 505)
      The sermons on MATT. 25:1-12 form a series of nine sermons on the parable of the ten virgins
    - MATT. 25:1-12: "1. Wherein true and false Christians in general agree. 2. Wherein true and false Christians do sometimes agree" (p. 2), 1737/8 Jan (Box 7, Folder 506)
    - MATT. 25:1-12: [More about wherein true and false Christians may agree], 1737/8 [Jan] (Box 7, Folder 507)
    - MATT. 25:1-12: [More about ways in which true and false Christians agree], 1737/8 Feb (Box 7, Folder 508)
    - MATT. 25:1-12: "Wherein true and false Christians differ", 1738 (Box 7, Folder 509)
    - MATT. 25:1-12: "Application", 1738 (Box 7, Folder 510)
    - MATT. 25:1-12: [More wherein true and false Christians differ], 1738 (Box 7, Folder 511)
    - MATT. 25:1-12: "The consequences [in difference between true and false Christians] with respect to their hopes of a state of grace", 1738 (Box 7, Folder 512)
    - MATT. 25:1-12: [Differences in their general character], 1738 (Box 7, Folder 513)
    - MATT. 25:1-13: "Obs. 1. Christ is the bridegroom of the church. 2. Professours of religion in general hope to go to heaven. 3. Many of the professours are not true Christians..." (p. 1), 1752 Dec
      See: Box 13, folder 1046
    - MATT. 25:8: "That the religion of hypocrites is not of a durable nature" (p. 4), n.d. (Box 7, Folder 514)
    - MATT. 25:10: "The shutting of the door of mercy" (p. 1), 1742, 1756 (Box 7, Folder 515)
    - MATT. 25:24-28: "Doc. 1. Discouragement [in seeking salvation often arises] from slothfulness... 2. Slothful persons are very ready to lay the blame of their unprofitableness to God..." (pp. 14, 34), incomplete, [ca. 1730's] (Box 7, Folder 516)
    - MATT. 25:40: "Christ in all the glory that he will appear in at the day of judgment will openly receive and treat the saints as his brethren" (p. 1), 1743 Dec (Box 7, Folder 517)
      "Contribution lecture"
    - MATT. 25:46: "The misery of the wicked in hell will be absolutely eternal" (p. 2), 1739 Apr (Box 7, Folder 518)
    - MATT. 28:6-7: "1. How he rose... 2. Evidence of his resurrection... 3. Why it was necessary" (pp. 2-3), 1754 Feb
      See: Box 13, folder 1047
    - MATT. 28:9: "We ought to exercise the most dear, humble and adoring respect to the Lord Jesus Christ" (p. 5), 1733 Oct (Box 7, Folder 519)
    - MATT. 28:19-20: "4. They that are baptized are under great obligations to observe all the commands of Christ" (p. 2), incomplete, [1751-57?]
      See: Box 13, folder 1048
    - MARK 1:7: "Application. If so great a person as John the Baptist was not worthy to stoop down [and loose the latchet of Christ's shoes], then how wonderful it is that Christ should stoop so low for men" (p. 5), 1742 Jul (Box 7, Folder 520)
    - MARK 2:17: "What induces Christ to pity and help sinners is not that they deserve it but that they need it" (p. 3), 1741 Jun (Box 7, Folder 521)
    - MARK 5:16-17: "Observation. The Gadarenes loved their swine better than Jesus Christ" (p. 6), 1737 Apr (Box 7, Folder 522)
    - MARK 5:32-34: "Tis never taken as any indecent boldness in any to come to Christ for help and comfort under any difficulties" (p. 1), 1752 May 26 (Box 7, Folder 523)
      "Northampton at Capt. Dwight's"
    - MARK 6:17-20: "There are many persons that would feign have salvation and do many things for it, and yet there are some particular sins that they will not part with" (p. 3), 1733-53 (Box 7, Folder 524)
    - MARK 6:45: "1. Hence we need not wonder that persons sometimes cry out for fear, when God appears to them as their enemy under spiritual distresses and difficulties [application]" (p. 5), 1741 Dec (Box 7, Folder 525)
    - MARK 8:38: "That Christ will here after treat those that have continued in unbelief under the gospel as he has been treated by 'em in this world" (p. 4), 1737, 1753 (Box 7, Folder 526)
    - MARK 9:44: "That the torments of hell will be eternal" (p. 3), n.d. (Box 7, Folder 527)
    - MARK 10:17-27: "Obs. 1. There are many persons that have a great desire to have eternal life and seek it with some earnestness, that yet never obtain it" (p. 2), 1743, 1757 (Box 7, Folder 528)
    - MARK 10:17-27: "Obs. 6. The commands of the second table of the law rightly understood are very proper for the trial of persons' obedience" (p. 1), [1743], 1757 (Box 7, Folder 529)
    - MARK 10:17-27: "Obs. 13. They that truly come to Christ come to Him after such a manner as in the same act to forsake all for Him" (p. 1), [1743], 1757 (Box 7, Folder 530)
    - MARK 10:17-27: "Obs. 16. If men have parted with the world for Christ in their hearts it may well be expected that they should make it manifest by actually parting with it as they are called" (p. 1), [1743], 1757 (Box 7, Folder 531)
    - MARK 10:17-27: "Obs. 18. They that truly come to Christ: they accept of His cross as well as His salvation" (p. 1), [1743], 1757 (Box 7, Folder 532)
    - MARK 10:17-27: "Obs. 22. Carnal men may seem to be with Christ and to be good friends with Him a little while but are wont soon to fall out with Him and forsake him" (p. 1), [1743], 1757 (Box 7, Folder 533)
    - MARK 10:17-27: "Obs. 25. Riches are commonly a great hindrance on the way of men's salvation" (p. 1), [1743, 1757?] (Box 7, Folder 534)
    - MARK 10:17-27: "Obs. 26. Christ when upon earth was wont to treat his disciples with wonderful tenderness and true gentleness" (p. 1), [1743, 1757?] (Box 7, Folder 535)
    - MARK 10:17-27: "Obs. 1. There are many that have a great desire to have eternal life and take considerable pains for it that yet never obtain it" (p. 1), 1754 Feb
      See: Box 13, folder 1049
    - MARK 10:32-34: "Christ's behaviour when the time of his death drew near was very wonderful" (p. 2), 1749 Oct (Box 7, Folder 536)
    - MARK 10:49: "Tis sufficient warrant to any to come to Christ that Christ calls them" (p. 4), 1735/6 Jan (Box 7, Folder 537)
    - MARK 14:3: "1. I shall briefly take notice of the nature and circumstances of the external act of this woman [Mary]. 2. Observe how it was resented by Jesus Christ on whom the act was done. 3. Give the reason why it was so resented..." (p. 1), 1741 May (Box 7, Folder 538)
    - MARK 16:5: "The heavenly inhabitants do as it were remain in eternal youth" (p. 2), 1747 Nov (Box 7, Folder 539)
    - MARK 16:15-16: "What is meant by believing in Christ. For a man to believe in Christ is to come to him with all the heart, to take him for his Saviour and give himself to him, to be one of his people, and to have all his dependence on Christ to make him happy" (p. 3), 1750/1, 1752
      See: Box 13, folder 1050
    - LUKE 1:17: "After a dead time in religion tis very requisite that religion should revive in heads of families and those that have the care of children in order to a people's being fitted for so great a privilege as to have God remarkably dwelling among them" (p. 1), 1741 Aug (Box 7, Folder 540)
      "Meeting of middle aged people, from 26 to 50"
    - LUKE 1:77-79: "How a sinner that has offended God should be reconciled to him again and restored to his favor, could be known no other way but by divine revelation", 1739, 1756 (Box 7, Folder 541)
      "Lecture," "at New Haven"
    - LUKE 1:77-79: "I. God's people have the forgiveness of their sins by Jesus Christ" (p. 1), 1753 Dec
      See: Box 13, folder 1051
    - LUKE 2:6-14: "I. What was that was born of the virgin... II. Who he was born for... III. What need there was of his being born and being man" (p. 1), 1753 Dec
      See: Box 13, folder 1052
    - LUKE 2:10-11: "The word of God which tells us about Jesus Christ is good news" (p. 1), 1756 Apr
      See: Box 13, folder 1053
      "Stockbridge"
    - LUKE 2:14: "That the Son of God by appearing in our nature laid a glorious foundation for peace to the inhabitants of this world" (p. 2)
      See: Box 13, folder 1054
    - LUKE 2:14: "That Christ's appearing in our nature is an instance of wonderful love to man" (p. 2)
      See: Box 13, folder 1055
    - LUKE 2:25-38: "It becomes aged men and women amongst the people of God with peculiar love and joy to receive Christ when He comes and extraordinarily manifests himself in the world" (p. 1), 1741 Aug (Box 7, Folder 542)
      "To old people"
    - LUKE 3:9: "1. The time of the approach of the setting up of the kingdom of heaven in the latter days, as appears by Scripture, is very parallel with the time that John the Baptist lived..." (p. 2), n.d. (Box 7, Folder 543)
    - LUKE 4:18: "I. Shew you how the Spirit of God was given to Christ" (p. 1), 1755 Jul
      See: Box 13, folder 1056
    - LUKE 4:38-39: "When persons are restored from dangerous sickness their business should be to serve and minister to him that has restored them" (p. 4), 1738/9 Jan (Box 7, Folder 544)
    - LUKE 5:5-6: "That it is our best way in all cases to follow the directions that Christ gives us", n.d.
      See: Box 13, folder 1057
    - LUKE 6:24: "That all the pleasure or comfort that ever wicked men are to have they have in this life" (p. 3) (Box 7, Folder 545)
    - LUKE 6:35: "God is kind to the unthankful and to the evil, and this appears in his great kindness to mankind who are the subjects of abundance of the kindness and goodness of God and yet are very evil and unthankful" (p. 2), 1755, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 546)
    - LUKE 6:45: "The speech of their mouths will shew that which their heart is full of" (p. 1), 1753 Aug
      See: Box 13, folder 1058
    - LUKE 6:45: "I. A good man has a good treasure in his heart..." (p. 1), 1753 Aug (Box 7, Folder 547)
      Written on the back of Jonathan Edwards's rough draft of proposals for printing the Reply to Williams, preached to Stockbridge Indians
    - LUKE 6:45: "I. A wicked man has a treasure of evil in his heart" (p. 1), 1753 Aug
      See: Box 13, folder 1059
    - LUKE 6:48: "They that would build an hope of heaven well should dig deep and lay their foundation on a rock" (p. 2), 1738/9 Jan (Box 7, Folder 548)
    - LUKE 7:35: "All true saints justify the gospel of Jesus Christ" (p. 1), 1747 Jul (Box 7, Folder 549)
    - LUKE 8:2-3: "When Christ has delivered persons from the power of Satan tis very becoming of them to shew their love to Christ by ministering to him of their substance" (p. 7), 1739 Nov (Box 7, Folder 550)
    - LUKE 8:26-39: "II. How wicked men are like the man possessed with devils" (p. 1), 1754 Jun
      See: Box 13, folder 1060
    - LUKE 8:27: "Obs. 1. Men as they are by nature are possessed with devils" (p. 2), 1741/2 Jan (Box 7, Folder 551)
    - LUKE 8:28: "That there is no goodness in praying though it never be so earnestly merely out of a fear of misery" (p. 4), n.d. (Box 7, Folder 552)
    - LUKE 9:18: "True Christians differ from all the world in their thoughts of Jesus Christ" (p. 4), n.d. (Box 7, Folder 553)
    - LUKE 9:23: "That if we would be Christ's disciples it is necessary that we should deny ourselves" (p. 3), n.d.
      See: Box 13, folder 1061
    - LUKE 9:23: "I. Why it is necessary for a man if he would be a true Christian must deny himself" (p. 1), 1755 Aug
      See: Box 13, folder 1062
    - LUKE 9:30-31: "The death of Christ is a great subject of contemplation and discourse among the saints in glory" (p. 1), 1748, 1751 (Box 7, Folder 554)
    - LUKE 9:51: "The subject: that Jesus Christ's steadfastness in going through with those labors and sufferings that he came into the world for" (p. 1), 1746, 1757 (Box 7, Folder 555)
    - LUKE 9:56: "Christ came into the world to save men's lives" (p. 1), 1754 Sep
      See: Box 13, folder 1063
    - LUKE 9:61-62: "Looking back after persons have once engaged is especially disagreeable and mischievous in religion" (p. 4), 1739 Sep (Box 7, Folder 556)
    - LUKE 10:2: "1. Consider the character under which God is here spoken of, viz. the Lord of the harvest. 2. Consider the duty here directed to..." (p. 3), 1758, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 557)
    - LUKE 10:11: "Those who have had the kingdom of God brought nigh to them and have rejected it would do well to remember and thoroughly consider that the kingdom of God has been nigh to them" (p. 5), 1735/6 Jan (Box 7, Folder 558)
    - LUKE 10:17-18: "When those ministers of the gospel that have been faithful and successful come to give an account of their success to their Lord that hath sent them Christ and they will rejoice together" (p. 5), 1736, 1751 (Box 7, Folder 559)
      "Ordination at Lambstown" 1736 Nov 17
    - LUKE 10:38-42: "Doc. [1]. The way to receive spiritual knowledge and wisdom is to sit at Jesus' feet and hear his word. (p. 5) "Doc. 2. The most acceptable way of shewing respect to Christ is to give hearty entertainment to his word." (p. 21) "Doc. 3. Anxiousness and fullness of cares about the things of this world is inconsistent with our minding the great concerns of our souls as we ought to do" (p. 41), 1754, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 560)
    - LUKE 10:42: "1. That grace is the one thing needful. (p. 2) "2. True grace is the good part. Tis called the good part by way of eminency as being incomparably the best part" (p. 9), 1752, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 561)
    - LUKE 10:42: "That which God gives to the saints for their part is the best good that ever any of the children of men obtain" (p. 3), 1740, 1754 (Box 7, Folder 562)
    - LUKE 11:13: "Of the more excellent nature any blessing is that we stand in need of the more ready God is to bestow it in answer to prayer" (p. 5), 1740 Nov (Box 7, Folder 563)
      "Fast for pouring out of the Spirit"
    - LUKE 11:21-22: "The conquering power of God gloriously appears in the saving work of his spirit on the soul", 1739, 1750 (Box 7, Folder 564)
    - LUKE 11:24-26: "I. The devil naturally dwells in the hearts of men" (p. 1), 1755 Jul
      See: Box 13, folder 1064
    - LUKE 11:27-28: "That the hearing and keeping the word of God renders a person more blessed than any other privilege that ever God bestowed on any of the children of men" (p. 2), 1751, n.d.
      See: Box 14, folder 1065
    - LUKE 12:4-5: "1. The worst evils that the power of men can inflict are as nothing in comparison of damnation. 2. Tis a thing of great importance that persons be thoroughly possessed with a dread of the wrath and vengeance of God" (p. 2) (Box 7, Folder 565)
    - LUKE 12:16-21: "Doc. I. God oftentimes gives those men that he hates great outward prosperity" (p. 1), 1749 Dec (Box 7, Folder 566)
    - LUKE 12:35-36: "Men ought so to improve the time of life that when they come to die they may have nothing to do but to die" (p. 2), 1742-54 (Box 8, Folder 567)
    - LUKE 12:44: "True saints who acquit themselves as Christ's faithful servants and stewards in this world, in the world to come shall be admitted to the possession of his whole estate" (p. 1), 1749 Dec (Box 8, Folder 568)
    - LUKE 13:5: "Without true repentance for sin there is no escaping eternal ruin" (p. 3), n.d.
      See: Box 14, folder 1066
    - LUKE 13:7: "A people that live under the gospel are as it were God's orchard" (p. 1), 1751 Jun
      See: Box 14, folder 1067
    - LUKE 13:7: "God does as it were cause you to see whether those that lie under the gospel do bring forth good fruit", 1753 Jan (Box 8, Folder 569)
      New Year's Day to the Stockbridge Indians
    - LUKE 13:24: [Text: Strive to enter at the strait gate], fragment, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 570)
    - LUKE 13:28: Begins: "Will not be with/ Separated. /Great gulf...", n.d. (Box 8, Folder 571)
    - LUKE 13:28-29: "Wicked men will hereafter will have this to aggravate their woe that they shall see many of all kinds and nations admitted into glory when they themselves are thrust out" (p. 3) (Box 8, Folder 572)
      "This I have preached at New Place," "Preached this at Chickaby," preached to Stockbridge Indians"
    - LUKE 13:30: "That some that seem to be first among professors in this world will appear to be last in the other world and so on the contrary some that are last will be first" (p. 3) (Box 8, Folder 573)
    - LUKE 14:16: "Obs. 1. The provision which God has made for the good for the souls of men by Jesus Christ is like a great feast" (p. 1), 1752 Nov
      See: Box 14, folder 1068
    - LUKE 14:16-24: "1. Briefly explain the parable. 2. Observe how it was verified in Christ and the apostles' days. 3. Observe how this parable is adapted to our case and how applicable it is for our instruction and warning that live in these days and in this place. 4. Conclude with an agreeable exhortation" (p. 1), 1746 Apr (Box 8, Folder 574)
      "On occasion of the news of Mr. Brainard's success among the Indians/ Lecture before the sacrament"
    - LUKE 14:26: "They that have seemingly come to Christ that don't love Christ far above their dearest earthly enjoyments, they are not Christ's disciples" (p. 2), 1744 May (Box 8, Folder 575)
    - LUKE 15:3-7: "Christ is to his people as a shepherd to his flock" (p. 1), 1752 Nov
      See: Box 14, folder 1069
    - LUKE 15:11-24: "I. God is the Father of mankind... II. Wicked men are not willing to serve God but have a mind to be for themselves and not for God" (p. 1), 1753 Dec
      See: Box 14, folder 1070